<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>What happens when you type a URL into your browser?</title>
    <link href="/dukeding.github.io/2023/02/10/What-happens-when-you-type-a-URL-into-your-browser/"/>
    <url>/dukeding.github.io/2023/02/10/What-happens-when-you-type-a-URL-into-your-browser/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="1-Browser-look-up-IP-address-for-the-domain"><a href="#1-Browser-look-up-IP-address-for-the-domain" class="headerlink" title="1. Browser look up IP address for the domain"></a>1. Browser look up IP address for the domain</h2><p>After you have typed the URL on the browser, and press the enter button, the browser needs to figures out which server on the internet to connect to. The browser checks its own cache, system cache, router cache and DNS server cache. If the browser cannot find the ip address at any of those cache layers, the DNS server at you ISP does a recursive DNS lookup.</p><h2 id="2-Browser-initiates-TCP-connection-with-server"><a href="#2-Browser-initiates-TCP-connection-with-server" class="headerlink" title="2. Browser initiates TCP connection with server"></a>2. Browser initiates TCP connection with server</h2><p>The client browser establishes a TCP connection with the server through a three-way handshake.<br><br/></p><ul><li>Step1: Client initiates connection request</li><li>Step2: Server responds to connection request</li><li>Step3: Client acknowledge the connection</li></ul><p>Why is it necessary to initiate a TCP connection before sending an HTTP request?<br><br/><br><em>Because HTTP is an application-layer protocol that relies on the underlying transport-layer protocol, which is usually TCP(transmission control protocol).</em><br><img src="/dukeding.github.io/img/fluid/http.png" alt="tcp and http connection"></p><h2 id="3-Browser-send-the-HTTP-request-to-the-server"><a href="#3-Browser-send-the-HTTP-request-to-the-server" class="headerlink" title="3. Browser send the HTTP request to the server"></a>3. Browser send the HTTP request to the server</h2><p>After establishing the TCP connection, the browser has a connection to the server. It starts with the browser sending an http request to the server to request the content, this may involve HTML files, CSS, JavaScript, images, videos and so on”.</p><p>What content includes in the http request header?</p><ul><li>The request path</li><li>The request method, which is one of GET, POST, PUT, PATCH, DELETE<br/>What is the difference between HTTP and HTTPS?<br/></li></ul><table><thead><tr><th align="left"></th><th align="left">HTTP</th><th align="left">HTTPS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Security</td><td align="left">Plain text transmission</td><td align="left">Encrypted transmission using TLS&#x2F;SSL</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Default Port</td><td align="left">80</td><td align="left">443</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Protocol</td><td align="left">Standard HTTP protocol</td><td align="left">TLS&#x2F;SSL protocol added on top of HTTP</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Certificate</td><td align="left">Not required</td><td align="left">Server need a digital certificate for authentication</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 id="4-Server-processes-the-request-and-sends-back-a-response"><a href="#4-Server-processes-the-request-and-sends-back-a-response" class="headerlink" title="4. Server processes the request and sends back a response"></a>4. Server processes the request and sends back a response</h2><p>For server received the request based on the request line, headers and body decided to how to process the request.</p><p>What content includes in the http <strong>response</strong> header?</p><ul><li><em>The Content-Type, which is one of text&#x2F;plain, text&#x2F;html, text&#x2F;css, text&#x2F;xml, text&#x2F;javascript,  application&#x2F;json</em></li><li><em>Content-length</em></li><li><em>Content-Encoding</em></li><li><em>Cache-Control</em></li><li><em>Expires</em></li><li><em>Last-modified</em></li></ul><h2 id="5-Browser-renders-the-content"><a href="#5-Browser-renders-the-content" class="headerlink" title="5. Browser renders the content"></a>5. Browser renders the content</h2><p>Once the browser received the response from the server, it inspects the response headers for information on how to render the resource. The Content-Type in header tells the browser it received a html file or others.</p><p>What are the steps of rendering?</p><ul><li>Process the HTML file to build DOM tree</li><li>Process the CSS file to build CSSOM tree  </li><li>Merge the DOM tree and CSSOM tree into the Render tree</li><li>Layout(relfow) of the render tree is responsible for calculating the dimensions and position of each element</li><li>Paint each element on the screen</li></ul><h2 id="Reinforcing-Knowledge"><a href="#Reinforcing-Knowledge" class="headerlink" title="Reinforcing Knowledge"></a>Reinforcing Knowledge</h2><p>Browsers use HTTP as an application layer protocol to encapsulate the text information of requests; And using TCP protocol as the transport layer protocol, it is necessary to establish a TCP connection with the server before sending HTTP requests</p><p><img src="/dukeding.github.io/img/fluid/network-layer.png" alt="network layer"></p>]]></content>
    
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>computer network</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
